United States and Canada
Story of the surfer picture
I'm from California. There were surfers there and there are surfers here.
A little illogical, but they're in the United States.
And people say if there are surfers there then why are you here?
Well, I don't need a wetsuit
Ok. North American cultural contributions
So I was playing with the toys when you came in.
If I were to pick something to play that people would truly consider American
I would' what band music would I play
Jazz. That is one of the things that make us very American
Jazz is a mix. What you need to know, take a guess
It's a mix of two different musical traditions
Where might one of these traditions be from?
Absolutely. So Africa absolutely because you have your founders slave culture there.
And Spain, yes, but we get even bigger'
Spain's part of'? Europe! Yes.
And definitely you have some of jazz coming from that too in Europe
So jazz is a mixture of African heritage and European classical
Spain would fit into that plus some of the other traditions.
And now it is quintessentially American, which already says so much becaus
it is from traditions and peoples that are not of this land
Theirs becomes ours and that's how we get a lot of things here.
So, alright.
You can see, this is a picture of the United States
And I tried to cut off this line, but keep this really important state.
What I have cut off here is Mexico. Some people would call that north America
Depending on how you feel about it, it's really latin America
So really we will talk about that next week
Ok. 48 contiguous states. And everyone says 'oh I learned that in 6th grade.'
Contiguous. What does that mean? Contiguous. Yes!
That they're next to each other. They're connected to each other
We have 48 contiguous states, but we know that we have more than that
We have two non-contiguous states. What and what?
Alaska and' Hawaii. Wonder how we got the
Alright. Canada. Canada is big. And that's actually important
We thought the Russian Federation was huge, well second to that is Canada
So this is important.
Important part of the world and an important part of our connection.
So north America, in the way, way north we go up into the Arctic
I have a picture of Alaska here
Obviously this is out of my hotel, and it's not a really nice hotel
I had taken this picture at 11 o'clock and this continues to fascinate me
Is this 11 am or pm
Pm! And' I just' that just trips me out.
So I'm here winter or summer? Summer. Very much in summer
Winter, it would be dark for most of the time.
And also, again
the span of this area we're talking about goes all the way down to the south
Subtropical
What is the most subtropical place in the United States? Florida
Yes, and actually somebody said Hawaii
which actually wasn't terrible but they're actually sort of tropical
Ok. So when we're talking about Canada and the United States
common physical resources
We have minerals. Fisheries. This is not my picture.
I was in Alaska and I was very excited
Oh I'm going to stand on a bridge and see' what were they waiting for
Salmon. It was going to be so cool and I looked ove
and was going to take a picture and I waited and' nothing
So I got this fine individual. Fertile land.
A lot of farming. Most of it looks like this.
Forests. Kind of interesting since both places have forests
but none of the textbooks discuss this. Wildlife.
Ah! Not my picture
But that, with the little black blob' that's my picture
Student: Black bear?) yes
It is a black bear. Who has seen a bear?
Yes you all are way ahead of all of us.
So we see this black blob and we're driving on and I'm like 'oh! This is so exciting!
and we get out and the bear is trundling off
And we see it sitting, and it's eating berries. And it's just
when you see a bear and you see an animal in the wild just doing its thing
it's just' really incredible
So we went and we took the picture. And it was our first night in.
And they said, 'oh well did you hear about the hiker
Yesterday he was killed and eaten by a bear.'
Maybe not a black bear, but a grizzly.
And they said 'yeah a black bear'.
Oh. Who's seen 'The Revenant'?
ok, I gotta be honest, but there's a bear scene and that made me more worried than I was.
So, I went out the next morning and I went for my little jog.
And I feel very clever and I [inaudible].
And it's even got the little maple leaves because it's Canad
So, I'm going out for my run, and [inaudible]. So I'm going for my run, and I walk into a bear.
And I'm here and they're about where you guys are there.
And all I can think of is 'I can't outrun a bear'.
So I just back up slowly and there's a little river creek thing
And I'm thinking I will go to the water, and then the bear won't get me
A bear is afraid of water? And then I was like, 'wait no. that's a bad idea.'
And then I thought act big and act scary!
So I'm looking at the bear and I go *roar*
And you know how animals do that thing where they just cock their head?
And then I got scared and thought it was going to eat me. And then I just [inaudible]
So I'm looking at it and I just *noise*. And it just looks at me and it just walked off.
(Student: inaudible) Well, that's probably another thing I should've done.
So now I have to decide what to do. Do I go back? Do I go forward? And I *shakes bells*.
And you're supposed to let the bear know you are coming.
And if it knows you are coming, it is not supposed to be interested in you.
It's when you shock it that it has a tendency to eat you. So that's my bear experience.
Bighorn sheep. I remember driving in the car and I said, 'oh I want to get a picture.'
And they started coming into the window. And I said 'ooo! I can take a picture!'.
Another thing that they say we have in common is physical beauty, which always makes me laugh.
But that's something that we have in common.
This top left is Alaska on a train ride going up into the mountains and it's beautiful.
And Canada, again, it is truly, truly beautiful landscape.
Ok. Another thing that we do well in the United States and Canada is we use our technology to exploit our sources.
So one example of that would be going down the Mississippi river.
This is a big river, but what did we build? (Student: canals?) Canals and' levees!
Now the reason why is that the Mississippi river is a meandering river
So a meandering river moves like this.
So it will go this way, and then this way. Ok so it's not straight.
So a meandering river, what it does, is it changes its course
The way a river flows, the outside part is faster.
So it manages just to cut out further, so the whole thing will start to move over
So you have this moving river, and you want your towns to be nearest to water
And people settle near the river.
Now, everyone is excited.
'We got that river front, yay!' and now the river is going to come and wipe out and ugh.
So they built the levees. We are controlling our resources
We are using our technology to control it
So you can have the river, you can be close to it, but the river doesn't wipe you out
It doesn't do it's natural course.
Now, clearly we do what we can. Katrina. What happened to those levees? They broke!
So again, we do what we can to control nature. But at some point, there is only so much we can do
With Katrina the levee broke, and [inaudible].
So some of the results of this are a really high standard of living in both of these places.
Here's a picture of Vancouver. Some people have been to Vancouver, it's a beautiful city.
And as a result, they get a lot of pollution.
That picture, that I took from California, I'm from northern California.
This is from somewhere in California famous for their smog. What city is this? Los Angeles.
That's Los Angeles [inaudible].